<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<rfc docName="draft-ietf-grow-bgp-gshut-06" ipr="pre5378Trust200902" category="info">
    <front>
        <title>Graceful BGP session shutdown</title>
        <author surname="Francois" initials="P." fullname="Pierre Francois">
            <organization>Institute IMDEA Networks</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Avda. del Mar Mediterráneo, 22</street>
                    <city>Leganese</city>
                    <code>28918</code>
                    <country>ES</country>
                </postal>
                <email>pierre.francois@imdea.org</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author surname="Decraene" initials="B." fullname="Bruno Decraene">
            <organization>France Telecom</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>38-40 rue du General Leclerc</street>
                    <city>92794 Issy Moulineaux cedex 9</city>
                    <code/>
                    <country>FR</country>
                </postal>
                <email>bruno.decraene@orange.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author surname="Pelsser" initials="C." fullname="Cristel Pelsser">
            <organization>Internet Initiative Japan</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Jinbocho Mitsui Bldg.</street>
                    <street>1-105 Kanda Jinbo-cho</street>
                    <city>Tokyo</city>
                    <code>101-0051</code>
                    <country>JP</country>
                </postal>
                <email>cristel@iij.ad.jp</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author surname="Patel" initials="P." fullname="Keyur Patel">
            <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>   170 West Tasman Dr</street>
                    <city>San Jose, CA</city>
                    <code>95134</code>
                    <country>US</country>
                </postal>
                <email>keyupate@cisco.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author surname="Filsfils" initials="C." fullname="Clarence Filsfils">
            <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>De kleetlaan 6a </street>
                    <city>Diegem</city>
                    <code>1831</code>
                    <country>BE</country>
                </postal>
                <email>cfilsfil@cisco.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date />
        <area>General</area>
        <keyword>I-D</keyword>
        <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
        <abstract>
            <t>This draft describes operational procedures aimed at reducing the
                amount of traffic lost during planned maintenances of routers or links,
                involving the shutdown of BGP peering sessions.</t>
        </abstract>
    </front>
    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction">
            <t>
                Routing changes in BGP can be caused by planned, maintenance
                operations. This document discusses operational procedures to be applied in
                order to reduce or eliminate losses of packets during the maintenance.
                These losses come from the transient lack of reachability during the BGP
                convergence following the shutdown of an eBGP peering session between two
                Autonomous System Border Routers (ASBR).
            </t>
            <t>
                This document presents procedures for the cases where the
                forwarding plane is impacted by the maintenance, hence when
                the use of Graceful Restart does not apply.
            </t>
            <t>
                The procedures described in this document can be applied to reduce or
                avoid packet loss for outbound and inbound traffic flows initially
                forwarded along the peering link to be shut down.  These procedures
                trigger, in both involved ASes, rerouting to the alternate path, while
                allowing routers to keep using old paths until alternate ones are learned, installed
                in the RIB and in the FIB.
                This ensures that routers always have a valid route available during the
                convergence process.
            </t>
            <t>
                The goal of the document is to meet the requirements described in <xref target="RFC6198"/> at best, without changing the BGP protocol.
            </t>
            <t>
                Still, it explains why reserving a community value for the
                purpose of BGP session graceful shutdown would reduce the
                management overhead bound with the solution. It would also
                allow vendors to provide an automatic graceful shutdown
                mechanism that does not require any router reconfiguration at
                maintenance time.
            </t>
            <t>
                The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
                "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
                and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
                described in RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Terminology">
            <t>
                g-shut initiator: a router on which the session shutdown
                is performed for the maintenance.
            </t>
            <t> 
                g-shut neighbor: a router that peers with the g-shut
                initiator via (one of) the session(s) to be shut down.
            </t>
            <t>
                Initiator AS: the Autonomous System of the g-shut initiator.
            </t>
            <t>
                Neighbor AS: the Autonomous System of the g-shut neighbor.
            </t>
            <t>
                Loss of Connectivity (LoC: the state when a router has
                no path towards an affected prefix.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Packet loss upon manual eBGP session shutdown" anchor="sec.loss">
            <t>
                Packets can be lost during a manual shutdown of an eBGP
                session for two reasons.
            </t>
            <t>
                First, routers involved in the convergence process can
                transiently lack of paths towards an affected prefix, and drop
                traffic destined to this prefix. This is because alternate
                paths can be hidden by nodes of an AS. This happens when the
                paths are not selected as best by the ASBR that receive them
                on an eBGP session, or by Route Reflectors that do not
                propagate them further in the iBGP topology because they do
                not select them as best.
            </t>
            <t>
                Second, within the AS, the FIB of routers can be transiently
                inconsistent during the BGP convergence and packets towards
                affected prefixes can loop and be dropped. Note that these
                loops only happen when ASBR-to-ASBR encapsulation is not used
                within the AS.
            </t>
            <t>
                This document only addresses the first reason.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Practices to avoid packet losses" anchor="sec.practices">
            <t>
                This section describes means for an ISP to reduce the
                transient loss of packets upon a manual shutdown of a BGP
                session.
            </t>
            <section title="Improving availability of alternate paths">
                <t>
                    All solutions that increase the availability of alternate
                    BGP paths at routers performing packet lookups in BGP tables such as
                    <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-best-external"/> and <xref target="RFC7911"/> help
                    in reducing the LoC bound with manual shutdown of eBGP
                    sessions.
                </t>
                <t>
                    One of such solutions increasing diversity in such a way that, at
                    any single step of the convergence process following the
                    eBGP session shutdown, a BGP router does not receive a
                    message withdrawing the only path it currently knows for a
                    given NLRI, allows for a simplified g-shut procedure.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Note that the LoC for the inbound traffic of the maintained router,
                    induced by a lack of alternate path propagation within the iBGP topology
                    of a neighboring AS is not under the control of the operator performing
                    the maintenance. The part of the procedure aimed at avoiding LoC for
                    incoming paths can thus be applied even if no LoC are expected for the
                    outgoing paths.
                </t>
            </section>
            <!--Improving availability of alternate paths-->
            <section title="Make before break convergence: g-shut" anchor="sec.summary">
                <t>
                    This section describes configurations and actions to be performed for the graceful shutdown of eBGP peering links.
                </t>
                <t>
                    The goal of this procedure is to let the paths being shutdown visible,
                    but with a lower LOCAL_PREF value, while alternate paths spread through
                    the iBGP topology. Instead of withdrawing the path, routers of an AS will
                    keep on using it until they become aware of alternate paths.
                </t>
                <section title="eBGP g-shut">
                    <section title="Pre-configuration" anchor="sec.summary.config">
                        <t>
                            On each ASBR supporting the g-shut procedure, an outbound BGP route policy is applied on all iBGP sessions of the ASBR, that:
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        <list style="symbols" hangIndent="5">
                            <t>
                                matches the g-shut community
                            </t>
                            <t>
                                sets the LOCAL_PREF attribute of the paths tagged with the
                                g-shut community to a low value
                            </t>
                            <t>
                                removes the g-shut community from the paths.
                            </t>
                            <t>
                                optionally, adds an AS specific g-shut community on
                                these paths to indicate that these are to be withdrawn
                                soon.  If some ingress ASBRs reset the LOCAL_PREF
                                attribute, this AS specific g-shut community will be
                                used to override other LOCAL_PREF preference changes.
                            </t>
                        </list>
                    </t>
                        <t>
                            Note that in the case where an AS is aggregating multiple routes under
                            a covering prefix, it is recommended to filter out the g-shut community
                            from the resulting aggregate BGP route.  By doing so, the setting of the g-shut
                            community on one of the aggregated routes will not let the entire
                            aggregate inherit the community. Not doing so would let the entire
                            aggregate undergo the g-shut behavior.
                        </t>
                    </section>
                    <section title="Operations at maintenance time" anchor="sec.summary.shut">
                        <t>
                            On the g-shut initiator, upon maintenance time, it is required to:
                        <list style="symbols">
                            <t>
                                apply an outbound BGP route policy on the maintained eBGP
                                session to tag the paths propagated over the session with
                                the g-shut community.  This will trigger the BGP
                                implementation to re-advertise all active routes previously
                                advertised, and tag them with the g-shut community.
                            </t>
                            <t>
                                apply an inbound BGP route policy on the maintained eBGP session to tag the
                                paths received over the session with the g-shut community.
                            </t>
                            <t>
                                wait for convergence to happen.
                            </t>
                            <t>
                                perform a BGP session shutdown.
                            </t>
                        </list>
                        </t>
                    </section>
                    <section title="BGP implementation support for G-Shut">
                        <t>
                            A BGP router implementation MAY provide features aimed at
                            automating the application of the graceful shutdown procedures
                            described above.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            Upon a session shutdown specified as graceful by the
                            operator, a BGP implementation supporting a g-shut feature SHOULD: 
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            <list style="numbers" hangIndent="5">
                                <t>
                                    On the eBGP side, update all the paths propagated over the corresponding eBGP
                                    session, tagging the GSHUT community to them. Any subsequent
                                    update sent to the session being gracefully shut down would be
                                    tagged with the GSHUT community.
                                </t>
                                <t>
                                    On the iBGP side, lower the LOCAL_PREF value of the paths received over the eBGP
                                    session being shut down, upon their propagation over iBGP sessions.
                                    Optionally, also tag these paths with an AS specific g-shut community.
                                    Note that alternatively, the LOCAL_PREF of the paths received over the
                                    eBGP session can be lowered on the g-shut initiator itself, instead of
                                    only when propagating over its iBGP sessions.
                                </t>
                                <t>
                                    Optionally shut down the session after a configured
                                    time.
                                </t>
                                <t>
                                    Prevent the GSHUT community from being inherited by a path
                                    that would aggregate some paths tagged with the GSHUT
                                    community. This behavior avoids the GSHUT procedure to be
                                    applied to the aggregate upon the graceful shutdown of one of
                                    its covered prefixes.
                                </t>
                            </list>
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            A BGP implementation supporting a g-shut feature SHOULD also automatically
                            install the BGP policies that are supposed to be configured, as decribed in
                            <xref target="sec.summary.config"/> for sessions over which g-shut
                            is to be supported.
                        </t>
                    </section>
                </section>
                <section title="iBGP g-shut">
                    <t>
                        If the iBGP topology is viable after the
                        maintenance of the session, i.e, if all BGP speakers
                        of the AS have an iBGP signaling path for all prefixes
                        advertised on this g-shut iBGP session, then the
                        shutdown of an iBGP session does not lead to transient
                        unreachability.
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section title="Router g-shut">
                    <t>
                        In the case of a shutdown of a router, a reconfiguration of the
                        outbound BGP route policies of the g-shut initiator SHOULD be performed to
                        set a low LOCAL_PREF value for the paths originated by the g-shut
                        initiator (e.g, BGP aggregates redistributed from other protocols,
                        including static routes).
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        This behavior is equivalent to the recommended
                        behavior for paths "redistributed" from eBGP sessions
                        to iBGP sessions in the case of the shutdown of an
                        ASBR.
                    </t>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section title="Forwarding modes and transient forwarding loops during convergence" anchor="sec.forwarding">
            <t>
                The g-shut procedure or the solutions improving the availability of alternate paths, do not change the fact that BGP convergence and the subsequent FIB updates are run independently on each router of the ASes.
                If the AS applying the solution does not rely on encapsulation to forward packets from the Ingress Border Router to the Egress Border Router, then transient forwarding loops and consequent packet losses can occur during the convergence process.
                If zero LoC is required, encapsulation is required between ASBRs of the AS.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Link Up cases">
            <t>
                We identify two potential causes for transient packet losses upon
                an eBGP link up event. The first one is local to the g-no-shut initiator,
                the second one is due to the BGP convergence following the injection of new
                best paths within the iBGP topology.
            </t>
            <section title="Unreachability local to the ASBR">
                <t>
                    An ASBR that selects as best a path received over a newly
                    brought up eBGP session may transiently drop traffic. This can
                    typically happen when the nexthop attribute differs from the IP
                    address of the eBGP peer, and the receiving ASBR has not yet
                    resolved the MAC address associated with the IP address of that
                    "third party" nexthop.
                </t>
                <t>
                    A BGP speaker implementation could avoid such losses by
                    ensuring that "third party" nexthops are resolved before
                    installing paths using these in the RIB.
                </t>
                <t>
                    If the link up event corresponds to an eBGP session that is being manually
                    brought up, over an already up multi-access link, then the
                    operator can ping third party nexthops that are expected to be
                    used before actually bringing the session up, or ping directed
                    broadcast the subnet IP address of the link. By proceeding like
                    this, the MAC addresses associated with these third party nexthops
                    will be resolved by the g-no-shut initiator.
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="iBGP convergence">
                <t>
                    Corner cases leading to LoC can occur during an eBGP link up event.
                </t>
                <t>
                    A typical example for such transient unreachability for a given
                    prefix is the following:
                </t>
                <t>
                    Let's consider 3 route reflectors RR1, RR2, RR3. There is a full mesh
                    of iBGP session between them.
                </t>
                <t>
                    <list style="empty" hangIndent="5">
                        <t>
                            1. RR1 is initially advertising the
                            current best path to the members of its iBGP RR
                            full-mesh. It propagated that path within its RR
                            full-mesh. RR2 knows only that path towards the prefix.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            2. RR3 receives a new best path originated by the "g-no-shut"
                            initiator, being one of its RR clients. RR3 selects it as best, and
                            propagates an UPDATE within its RR full-mesh, i.e., to RR1 and RR2.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            3. RR1 receives that path, reruns its decision process,
                            and picks this new path as best. As a result, RR1 withdraws
                            its previously announced best-path on the iBGP sessions of its RR full-mesh.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            4. If, for any reason, RR3 processes the withdraw
                            generated in step 3, before processing the update generated
                            in step 2, RR3 transiently suffers from unreachability for
                            the affected prefix.
                        </t>
                    </list>
                </t>
                <t>
                    The use of <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-best-external"/> among the RR of
                    the iBGP full-mesh can solve these corner cases by ensuring
                    that within an AS, the advertisement of a new route is not
                    translated into the withdraw of a former route.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Indeed, "best-external" ensures that an ASBR does not
                    withdraw a previously advertised (eBGP) path when it receives
                    an additional, preferred path over an iBGP session. Also,
                    "best-intra-cluster" ensures that a RR does not withdraw a
                    previously advertised (iBGP) path to its non clients
                    (e.g. other RRs in a mesh of RR) when it receives a new,
                    preferred path over an iBGP session.
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section title="IANA assigned g-shut BGP community">
            <t>
                Applying the g-shut procedure is rendered much easier with the use of a
                single g-shut community value which could be used on all eBGP sessions, for
                both inbound and outbound signaling.  The community value 0xFFFF0000 has been
                assigned by IANA for this purpose.
            </t>
            <t>
                For Internet routes, a non transitive extended community will be reserved
                from the pool defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-reserved-extended-communities"/>. Using such a community type allows
                for not leaking graceful signaling out of the AS boundaries, without the need to explicitly
                configure filters to strip the community off upon path propagation.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Security Considerations">
            <t>
                By providing the g-shut service to a neighboring AS, an ISP provides
                means to this neighbor to lower the LOCAL_PREF value assigned to the paths
                received from this neighbor.
            </t>
            <t>
                The neighbor could abuse the technique and do inbound traffic
                engineering by declaring some prefixes as undergoing a maintenance so as to
                switch traffic to another peering link.
            </t>
            <t>
                If this behavior is not tolerated by the ISP, it SHOULD monitor the use
                of the g-shut community by this neighbor.
            </t>
            <t>
                ASes using the regular (transitive) g-shut community SHOULD remove the
                community from neighboring ASes that do not support the g-shut procedure.
                Doing so prevents malignant remote ASes from using the community through
                intermediate ASes that do not support the feature, in order to perform
                inbound traffic engineering. ASes using the non-transitive extended
                community do not need to do this as the community is non transitive and
                hence cannot be used by remote ASes.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Acknowledgments">
            <t>
                The authors wish to thank Olivier Bonaventure and Pradosh Mohapatra
                for their useful comments on this work.
            </t>
        </section>
    </middle>
    <back>
        <references>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7911"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.I-D.draft-ietf-idr-best-external-05"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6198"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.I-D.draft-ietf-idr-reserved-extended-communities-09"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
        </references>
        <section title="Alternative techniques with limited applicability">
            <t>
                A few alternative techniques have been considered to provide
                g-shut capabilities but have been rejected due to their limited
                applicability.  This section describe them for possible
                reference.
            </t>
            <section title="Multi Exit Discriminator tweaking" anchor="sec.med-poison">
                <t>
                    The MED attribute of the paths to be avoided can be increased
                    so as to force the routers in the neighboring AS to select other
                    paths.
                </t>
                <t>
                    The solution only works if the alternate paths are as good as
                    the initial ones with respect to the Local-Pref value and the AS
                    Path Length value.  In the other cases, increasing the MED value
                    will not have an impact on the decision process of the routers in
                    the neighboring AS.
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="IGP distance Poisoning" anchor="sec.igp-poison">
                <t>
                    The distance to the BGP nexthop corresponding to the
                    maintained session can be increased in the IGP so that the old
                    paths will be less preferred during the application of the IGP
                    distance tie-break rule. However, this solution only works for the
                    paths whose alternates are as good as the old paths with respect
                    to their Local-Pref value, their AS Path length, and their MED
                    value.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Also, this poisoning cannot be applied when nexthop self is
                    used as there is no nexthop specific to the maintained session to
                    poison in the IGP.
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>
    </back>
</rfc>
